Preliminary Guide to the Joseph Marshall Flint Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joseph Marshall Flint papers
1862-1971
MS 1295
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
The papers consist of records and correspondence of Joseph Marshall Flint relating to the Mobile Hospital #39 in World War I.
Flint, Joseph Marshall, 1872-1944
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
In 1872, Joseph Marshall Flint was born in Chicago. Receiving his B.S. from the University of Chicago in 1895, Flint went on to Johns Hopkins University, where he received an M.D. in 1900. Between 1901 and 1907, he was professor of anatomy at the University of California. In 1903, while in California, Flint married Anne Apperson. In 1907, he became the first full-time professor of surgery at Yale Medical School. While in New Haven, he served as chief surgeon at the New Haven Hospital and New Haven Dispensary. When the United States entered World War I, Flint and his colleagues organized a medical unit to be sent to France. Knowing they did not have the resources to create a general hospital, they adopted a French concept and created Mobile Hospital Unit #39. Flint was director of this unit. He died on September 16, 1944, in Seal Harbor, Maine.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of records and correspondence of Joseph Marshall Flint relating to the Mobile Hospital #39 in World War I.
Medicine; Mobile hospitals; World War, 1914-1918; Flint, Joseph Marshall, 1872-1944
- Inventory
  - Orders and letters, Hospital Department, United States Army, 1862-1867 (Box 1)
  - Act Well Your Part and other creative writing pieces by Elizabeth Stephenson Williams (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence of J. M. Flint, 1903, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, induction papers, photographs, journal, and other materials relating to the creation and organization of Mobile Hospital #39, 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Reports on activities of Mobile Hospital #39, Circa 1919 (Box 1)
  - Reports on activities of Mobile Hospital #39, Circa 1919 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, clippings, histories, reports, photographs, and other materials relating to the 39th General Hospital, 1923-1971 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, clippings, histories, reports, photographs, and other materials relating to the 39th General Hospital, 1923-1971 (Box 4)
  - Journals, reports, published articles, indexes, and other materials relating to medical research and practice, 1918-1955 (Box 4)
  - Volume: "Series of Operated Fractures: Presented at Meeting of American Society of Clinical Surgery by Carleton P. Flint", 1907 October 18 (Box 5)
  - Records, correspondence re: Yale Hospital Unit in World War I (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook and loose photographs relating to Mobile Hospital #39 (Box 7)